Guide to the William Grant Still Papers, 1877-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Grant Still papers 1877-1992
Still, William Grant, 1895-1978
12.0 linear feet Extent: circa 2,250 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01255
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Duplication of the materials in the William Grant Still papers is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Grant Still Papers (1877-1992) were purchased by Duke University in 1992.
Biographical Note
1895, May 11 Born in Woodville, Miss.
1895 Moved to Little Rock, Ark. with mother, Carrie Fambro Still
1911 Matriculated at Wilberforce College
1915 Married Grace Bundy
1916 Employed in music publishing company of W. C. Handy and Charles Pace (Memphis, Tenn.) Played in W. C. Handy's band.
1917 Entered Oberlin Conservatory
1924 Composed Darker America
1929 Composed Breath of a Rose
1931 Rochester Philharmonic Orchestra performed Afro-American Symphony
1935 Composed Kaintuck
1934, 1935 and 1938 Won Guggenheim Fellowships
1938 Married Verna Arvey Commissioned to compose music for the 1939 New York World's Fair
1940 Arranged Katherine Garrison Chapin's poem, And They Lynched Him on a Tree
1941 Composed Bayou Legend Completed Troubled Island (Libretto by Langston Hughes and Verna Arvey)
1952 First full recording of Afro-American Symphony
1978, Dec. 3 Died in Los Angeles
Orchestras, including the New York Philharmonic and the Chicago Symphony, have performed Still's works throughout the United States. He received honorary degrees from the University of Arkansas, Wilberforce College, and Bates College.
Collection Overview
The William Grant Still Papers, 1877-1992, contain chiefly photocopies of music, writings, correspondence, diaries, pictures, printed material, clippings, and recordings, which primarily document his work as a composer. The collection relates to the historical and critical study of his music, as well as being a valuable source of arrangements for performances. Still's music gained recognition due to his ability to compose classical music which both reflected distinctive African-American as well as African influences. In addition, materials (primarily writings and librettos), created by Verna Arvey, Still's second wife, also form an integral part of the collection.
A substantial portion of the collection is comprised of music in manuscript and printed formats as well as in recorded formats, and is contained in the Music series and Recordings series. The collection does not contain all the music Still composed, however it does contain a substantial number of his works and can adequately support the research of Still's compositions. The various genres or mediums in which Still worked, including symphonies, operas, spirituals, songs, and chamber music are represented in the collection. Conductors' scores and published arrangements are included. Among the various publishers represented are Charles Pace and W.C. Handy Company and the J. Fischer and Brothers. Originals from these companies are present. Countee Cullen, Verna Arvey, Arna Bontemps, Langston Hughes, and Katherine Garrison Chapin are represented among those who wrote librettos or texts for Still's arrangements. Recordings for some of Still's works are available in compact disc, LP, and audio cassette formats. Included in the recordings are performances by Louis Kaufman, Peter Christ, Videmus, the William Grant Still Music Performing Arts Society, the Denver Symphony and San Francisco Symphony Orchestras, and other individual artists and orchestras.
Insofar as documenting Still's professional life, the diaries, writings, and correspondence are less complete than the music. Since gaps are evident within the diaries and correspondence, these materials do not provide a full and detailed understanding of Still's career development. However, some information pertaining to his work as well as his personal life is available. The Writings series contains several articles by Still as well as biographical and critical works about Still and his music. This series also contains writings by Verna Arvey and Judith Anne Still. An autographed copy of Arvey's In One Lifetime is included. The Correspondence series includes letters between Still and Alain Locke as well as Still and Charles Burch. Within these exchanges, there is some discussion and criticism of Still's compositions, reflections on the problems confronting African-American musicians in the 1930s, and a discussion of the possibility of Still teaching at Howard University. Correspondence between Arvey and Carl Van Vechten is also included. The diaries of both Still and Verna Arvey primarily record daily activities. However, Still's diary entries from 1930 contain reflections on his faith and spirituality, his music, and his first marriage to Grace Bundy. Within the Printed Materials and Clippings series are programs and newspaper articles, many of which are originals, that document the performances and the wide acceptance of Still's music.
The Scrapbooks series primarily contain Verna Arvey's collection of clippings which document political and social events between the 1940s and the early 1970s. These clippings demonstrate Verna Arvey's strong interest in the anti-Communist movements of the mid-twentieth century, primarily Senator Joseph McCarthy's investigations. The contents of these scrapbooks do not directly relate to William Grant Still's music. To a lesser extent the scrapbooks contain clippings pertaining to race and the status of African-Americans in the United States.
Subject Headings
Arvey, Verna, 1910-; Bontemps, Arna Wendell, 1902-1933; Chapin, Katherine Garrison, 1890-1977; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Kaufman, Louis, 1905-; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Burch, Charles; Music -- 20th century; Symphonies -- 20th century; Orchestral music -- 20th century; Opera -- 20th century; Chamber music -- 20th century; Spirituals (Songs); Music -- Manuscripts -- United States; Afro-American composers; Librettos; Scores; Opera; Songs; Diaries
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1924-1982, undated
  Includes photocopies of personal letters between Still and Alain Locke as well as letters between Still and Charles Burch. Correspondence between Verna Arvey and Carl Van Vechten is also included. Van Vechten was interested in photographing Still as well as acquiring Still manuscripts for the James Weldon Johnson Collection at Yale University.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1924, June-1982, July, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Diaries, 1928-1979. (Box 1)
  Contains photocopies of the diaries and daybooks of Still and Verna Arvey. Still's diary entries, especially from 1930, disclose information about his relationship with his first wife Grace Bundy and family financial struggles. The diaries also provide some insights into the progression of his compositions. Arvey's five-year diaries or daybooks record her daily activities. Arvey's earlier daybooks are more complete than the copies from the 1970s.
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Still, Verna Arvey, 1928-1979, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Still, William Grant, 1930; 1939, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks, 1877-1973, undated(bulk 1953-1973). (Box 1)
  Photocopies of Verna Arvey's "Racial-political-historical" scrapbook. The scrapbook primarily consists of articles from the Los Angeles Herald And Express and chronicles various major political events, especially the McCarthy investigations.
  - 1877-1954, Mar., (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1957, May 11-1968, July 21, (8 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1968, Oct 15-1973, Jan. 23, undated, (7 folders) (Box 4)
- Printed Material, 1930-1992, undated (Box 4)
  Includes programs and advertisements for various performances of William Grant Still's music. Primarily original materials with some photocopies.
  Arranged in chronological order by year.
  - 1930-1949, 1940s (Box 4)
  - 1954-1986, (8 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1987-1992, undated, (4 folders) (Box 6)
- Clippings, 1926-1989, undated (Box 6)
  Includes photocopies and originals of newspaper reviews of Still's music and performances of his works.
  - 1926-1992, undated, (5 folders) (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1936-1989, undated (Box 6)
  Includes copies of Still and Avery's wills and other legal documents, a statement of royalties, a puzzle, and proclamations recognizing Still. Chiefly photocopies.
  Arranged chronologically by year.
  - 1936-1991, undated (Box 6)
  - n.d (Box 7)
- Writings, 1929-1992, undated (Box 7)
  Primarily articles by Still and Verna Arvey, as well as books by Arvey and Judith Anne Still. Also included is an article by Langston Hughes pertaining to the libretto he wrote for Troubled Island, and articles by Alain Locke. Includes original publications and photocopies, no manuscript drafts are present.
  Primarily, articles and shorter works are arranged in chronological order by year and precede the books which are also arranged chronologically.
  - 1929-1985, (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1986-1992, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1941, Choreographic Music, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1984, In One Lifetime (Box 8)
  - 1990, William Grant Still: A Voice High-Sounding, (4 folders) (Box 9)
- Pictures, 1911-1949, undated (Box 9)
  Contains black and white images of Still and his family. Some of the images capture moments in Still's professional career.
  - 1911-1949, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
- Music, 1921-1991,n.d (Box 9)
  Comprised of the following subseries: Ballets, Cantatas, Chamber Music, Operas, Orchestras, Piano, Spiritual Arrangements, Songs, and Miscellaneous. The subseries reflect the various genres of music composed by William Grant Still.
  The subseries are arranged alphabetically and within each subseries the compositions are alphabetically by title. A complete list of the works within each genre has been prepared by a graduate student from the Duke University Department of Music and is in an information folder. The arrangement of the works in this collection is based upon that document, but does not follow it exactly. For further information, please consult a reference archivist. This series is comprised primarily of photocopies.
  - Ballets, 1941 and undated (Box 9)
    Includes the composer's notes for La Guiablesse and the arrangement and play for The Sorcerer.
    - D-S,1941, undated (Box 10)
  - Cantatas, 1931 (Box 10)
    Contains a J. Fischer and Bro. original of And They Lynched Him on A Tree.
    - A,1931 (Box 10)
  - Chamber Music, 1936-1964,(Oversize materials, 1936-1966, undated) (Box 10)
    Arrangements of Still's compositions by Anthony Griggs and Thomas Smith are included.
    - A-W, 1936-1991, undated, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Operas, 1976,n.d (Oversize materials, 1936-1963, undated) (Box 10)
    Included is a signed and inscribed copy of Bayou Legend and a conductor's score for The Pillar. Librettists for the various works include Bruce Forsythe, Langston Hughes, Frank Sherwood, and Verna Arvey.
    - A Bayou Legend, undated(Libretto only) (Box 10)
    - Troubled Island, 1976 (Libretto by Langston Hughes), (4 folders) (Box 10)
    - Troubled Island, undated(Libretto only) (Box 10)
  - Orchestras, 1937-1991, undated(Oversize materials, 1935-1959) (Box 10)
    Includes an original publication of Wood Notes and works by other composers which were orchestrated by Still.
    - C-S, 1937-1991, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Piano, 1916-1972 (Box 11)
    Contains pieces primarily written for piano instrumentation.
    - F-S, 1916-1972 (Box 11)
  - Songs, 1928-1973, undated(Oversize materials 1923-1943, undated) (Box 11)
    Contains Songs of Separations, for which lyrics were written by Langston Hughes, Arna Bontemps, Countee Cullen, and others. Other lyricists include Kate Chapin and Verna Arvey. Also includes From the Hearts of Women, Plainchant for America, Breath of A Rose, and a collection of Still's songs in Twelve Negro Spirituals published by Handy Brothers Publishing. Also contains folk songs composed by Still.
    - A-W, 1928-1973, undated, (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Spiritual arrangements, 1938-1981,n.d (Oversize materials,1941, undated) (Box 11)
    Includes an original of Ah Got a Home In-A Dat Rock printed by Charles Pace and W.C. Handy. Lyrics for some works were written by Verna Arvey. Contains some fragments.
    - A-W, 1938-1981,n.d, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Symphonies, undated(Oversize materials 1928-1946, undated) (Box 11)
    Includes full symphonies and symphonic poems, such as Darker America and Kaintuck The composer's notes for Symphony No.2 are present.
    - A-S, undated (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, undated(Oversize materials 1947-1975, undated) (Box 11)
    Contains band suites, solos pieces, sketches for Stormy Weather, children's music, and fragments.
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - A-S, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Opaperfolder 1-2, Box 11)
- Oversize Materials (Box 11)
  - Music Series (Box 11)
    - Ballets Subseries (Box 11)
      - B-T, 1933-1938, undated, (5 folders) (Box 12)
    - Cantatas Subseries (Box 12)
      - A,1931 (Box 13)
    - Chamber Music Subseries (Box 13)
      - B-V, 1936-1966, undated, (5 folders) (Box 13)
    - Operas Subseries (Box 13)
      - A Bayou Legend, undated, (7 folders) (Box 14)
      - Blue Steel, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
      - Blue Steel, undated, (4 folders) (Box 15)
      - Costaso, 1950, (4 folders) (Box 15)
      - Costaso, 1950, (3 folders) (Box 16)
      - From the Furnace of the Sun, 1936 (Box 16)
      - Highway 1, U.S.A., 1963, undated, (4 folders) (Box 16)
      - Minette Fontaine, undated, (6 folders) (Box 17)
      - Mota, undated, (4 folders) (Box 17)
      - Mota, undated, (3 folders) (Box 18)
      - The Pillar, 1955, undated, (6 folders) (Box 18)
      - Troubled Island, undated, (7 folders) (Box 19)
      - Troubled Island, undated, (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Orchestras Subseries (Box 20)
      - A-Am, 1935-1949, undated, (4 folders) (Box 20)
      - Ar-O, 1922-1959, undated, (7 folders) (Box 21)
      - Pa-Y, 1921-1959, undated, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - Piano (music for) Subseries (Box 22)
      - A, undated (Box 22)
      - A-F, 1923-1928, undated (Box 22)
      - L-W, 1937-1943, undated, (6 folders) (Box 23)
    - Spiritual Arrangements Series (Box 23)
      - G-S,1941, undated (Box 24)
    - Symphonies Subseries (Box 24)
      - A-S, 1928-1946, undated, (4 folders) (Box 24)
      - S, undated, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous Subseries (Box 25)
      - A-S, 1947-1975, undated, (3 folders) (Box 25)
- Recordings, 1935-1991, undated (Box 25)
  Primarily recordings of Still's music in audio cassettes, compact disc, and phonograph record formats. The recordings have been grouped together according to their respective formats. Recordings are arranged alphabetically within each format. The performing artists have been noted when they could be readily identified.
  Arranged alphabetically within each recording format.
  - Audio Tapes (Box 25)
    - Biography in Sound: Leopold Stowkowski, Stowkowski, Leopold,1954 (Box 26)
    - Calvacade of American Music, 1940, (4 tapes) (Box 26)
    - Ecosphere, Agus, Ayke et al.,1991 (Box 26)
    - Minette Fontaine, undated(2 tapes) (Box 26)
    - The Music of William Grant Still (2 tapes) (Box 26)
    - Oboist Peter Christ, Christ, Peter with the Crystal Chamber Soloists, 1979 (Box 26)
    - Our Musical Past-Vol. 5, The Royal Philharmonic Orchestra,1935 (Box 26)
    - Natalie Hinderas plays Piano Music, Hinderas, Natalie, undated (Box 26)
    - Royal Philharmonic Orchestra, The Royal Philharmonic Orchestra, n.d (Box 26)
    - Symphony No. 4, The Denver Symphony, undated (Box 26)
    - Troubled Island, undated(2 tapes) (Box 26)
    - William Grant Still, 1895-1978, The North Arkansas Symphony Orchestra et al., not before1978 (Box 26)
    - William Grant Still Conducts William Grant Still, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, 1984 (Box 26)
    - William Grant Still Piano Music, Dominguez, Albert, undated (Box 26)
    - William Grant Still: Strings, Keyboard and Harp, Kaufman, Louis et al., undated (Box 26)
    - William Grant Still: Voices and Piano, William Grant Still Performing Arts Society, undated (Box 26)
  - Compact Discs (Box 26)
    - Africa: Piano Music of William Grant Still, Oldham, Denver, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Lenox Avenue: The Music of William Grant Still, The CBS Symphony Orchestra et al.,1991 (Box 26)
    - Louis Kaufmann, Violin: Historic Recordings of 20th Century American Works, Kaufman, Louis, 1990 (Box 26)
    - Oboist Peter Christ, Christ, Peter with the Crystal Chamber soloists, 1986 (Box 26)
    - Our Musical Past- Vol. 5, The Royal Philharmonic Orchestra, 1935 (Box 26)
    - Walk as Children, Northern Arizona University Chorale, 1991 (Box 26)
    - Works by William Grant Still, Videmus,1990 (Box 26)
  - Phonograph Records (Box 26)
    - Art Songs by Black Composers, 1980, (2 LPs) (Box 27)
    - CBS Records Black Composers Series, 1987, (9 LPs) (Box 27)
    - William Grant Still 1895-1978, Ozark Chamber Players of the University Arkansas (Box 27)
    - William Grant Still Conducts William Grant Still, San Francisco Symphony Orchestra, 1984 (Box 27)
    - William Grant Still: Piano Music, Albert Dominguez,1987 (Box 27)
    - William Grant Still: Strings, Keyboard and Harp, Louis Kaufmann et al.,1987 (Box 27)
- Writings,1950 (Box 11)
- Printed Material,1991, undated (Box 11)